Welcome to Business Central Launch
Edition 2026 release wave one. My name
is Aleksandar Totovic. I'm product
manager and now I will try to explain
what is new in sustainability in
Business Central.
We invested in a last few releases a lot
of sustainability. This time you will
see a few features uh because we are
very close to finish this module. I say
the finish it will be treated as any
other module in a Business Central
because the most of features are already
delivered. Now we want to complete some
of them and this is actually what is
about in this release. So, first I will
start with some technical things.
What did we enable in this release? We
have now new sustainability APIs. If you
remember, if you used, we already have a
set of a lot of APIs related to
sustainability, but now we enable four
more.
We enable posted ESG reporting lines.
Method is only get. And what is about?
If you started to use um reporting for
uh CSRD and other types, depends in
which country you are, this is something
what we enabled in previous release. So,
you can do it directly in the Business
Central. You can calculate, you can
prepare reporting and you have by
default enabled integration with
external ESG reporting tool uh
Microsoft already delivered. So, we have
this native integration. You need to
have this license for Power Platform,
but this integration exists as native
integration. But, we said, "Okay, what
if from some reason you want to use some
other tool?" So, we are not limited only
for this one tool. This is by default.
This is enabled, but we do not want to
limit you. So, if you want to use any
other tool or if you want to use some
other reporting reason for whatever
reason you have, you can use now this
API posted ESG reporting line get. So,
you can collect all this information to
use in a regular report or some specific
compliance reporting tool. So, this is a
new.
We already enabled sustainability value
entry as API again get because you
cannot post into value entry directly
from outside of Business Central. So,
this is related with value chain scope
three. So, all these entries will come
directly when you post purchase
documents, sales document, production
document, and so on. But, if you need it
for external reporting or you you can
make some nice charts, whatever you
need, you can now use this API. And now
we have two APIs with a get, post, and
patch
methods.
First is sustainability purchase line.
So, now you we can combine this purchase
line with connect with another
softwares. Idea is to enable
calculations of carbon footprint and
other options directly on a purchase
line. So, this is a first step, so you
can connect with external software. And
if you have this information some
external software, you can collect and
import into Business Central purchase
lines. And the last one is about goals.
So, again, if you're using some external
third-party software, you can integrate
goals you configure in external software
with Business Central goals, so you can
easily track in a Business Central even
if you have third-party app.
What else we have?
Now we have new sales layout report
layouts. This may be not such a big
things, but more and more customers are
asking us, "Okay, we have all this
information." So, we have value chain,
we have automatic calculation through
all these from purchase, through
transfers, through manufacturing, and
sales. We have all this information, but
we need to show that.
So, now you have
in sales invoice, posted sales invoice,
you have two options, two new ESG
layouts. And the same for sales quote
because sometimes this exposure, what is
your carbon footprint, maybe will give
you a bit better chance to win when you
sell when you send a sales quote. So,
this is what we have and you can see
we have carbon equivalent
in our lines for each of lines and we
have for total. So, this is what we have
in both of these layouts. So, we expose
carbon footprint as a carbon carbon
equivalent information.
What else?
Let's say small
part. Actually, this is maybe beginning
of some
enabling some another integrations. We
have product classification item card.
It can be interesting if you want to
integrate this is what I mentioned with
this API. If you want to integrate with
some external sources about information.
So, by default you have blank, but you
can choose only one option in this
moment. So, we have only one option if
this is UNSPSC
option. This is UN standard product and
service code list. So, this list is
free. You can connect with this free
list and collect all carbon footprints
and all information about
items you are producing into your item
card. So, this integration doesn't
exist, but you have all prerequisites
here right now. After you choose this
option, you can choose product
classification. This is another table,
so you can fill or you can integrate
with the external software and you can
collect all of them. What is important?
We have only one option, but this is
extendable. So, if you have different
source, so if you have even paid source
with emission factors, you can easily
add another option and you can use all
this information from there.
So, this is about that. So, only what
you need to do is to have this product
classification codes and system will
handle all this information. In this
moment, we used this
option for OABL
electronic invoicing in Denmark
as a integration sustainability
information into e-documents as a pilot
program first time.
But again, it will be enabled for you
for your usage or for extending if you
need.
And the last feature
new carbon costing model.
This is actually our carbon
costing method actually. This is more
accurate
naming.
This is now in a public preview.
And now I want to show what exactly.
Previously, with no configuration
option, you had only average model. So,
this is the same as a costing method for
your costs, but it doesn't work with
your values, but with your carbon
footprint. Carbon equivalent actually.
So, you had earlier if you wanted to
track through your value chain, you had
default option average and you couldn't
change. You couldn't see this option
this it was only one and it was there.
But now, you have a new field on the
item card.
You can choose what you want to use.
You have new field carbon tracking
method and this is currently in a public
preview. So, by default is average
method. So, this is still by default and
why? If you already started to use value
chain, we didn't want to make any
breaking change. So, now this is only
this
exposed as option, but everything will
work exactly the same as previously. So,
this is in a GA. But we added new
specific method in addition as
additional option. And why we did it?
Uh to make probably the most accurate
model for carbon footprint tracking.
But what it requires, it requires item
tracking. So, you cannot use specific
method if you do not item tracking. It
uh assumes that you have item tracking
for serial numbers or lot numbers. So,
if you have this
um costing method already enabled, you
can enable specific method and it will
work the same way as uh we have specific
uh costing method in the Business
Central for
um
uh costs.
So, this is what we have new.
And now I would like to show you in a
short demo how it works.
First,
let's look in a posted sales invoice.
I'll choose the last one I have created.
When I go to report,
you can see report layout. Now, I can
choose another layout. I have standard
ESG sales invoice in Word and standard
ESG sales invoice blue. I will show one
of them and for quote I will show
another one. So, now if I click it, you
will get
all this information shows. So, you can
see carbon equivalent in kilograms.
These kilograms are coming from your
sustainability setup. You have per item.
Okay, and you have total carbon
equivalent in kilograms for whole
invoice.
So, this is if you're using invoices.
And if you use sales quote, as I
mentioned, we have this in sales quote
as well.
Okay, if you want to impress your
potential customers,
you can just go here and print. Again,
we have standard, but you can choose to
use again I don't want standard this
time I will use blue one, different
design.
And when I open preview,
again let's
see what we have. We have carbon
equivalent per unit and we have total
carbon equivalent in kilograms for whole
uh
sales quote. So, this is what we have
here and I just want shortly to switch
to items to show these new options.
Sorry.
So, now in sustainability fast tab,
you have carbon tracking method. As I
said, by default this is average, but
you can switch to specific if you have
specific model and enable serial numbers
or lots, whatever for item tracking, and
product classification. This is what I
said, you have UN SPCC,
and then you are code, so you can create
them manually, but in general, this is
created to enable you to make
integration with this source and then to
collect all their
um
sources of calculation in the system and
automatically populate all this
information about carbon carbon or
methane and other gas emissions.
So, this is what we have right now in
demo. This is what we have improved. We
are working on some other value chain
extensions, but in this moment, this is
what we deliver, and again, keep in mind
this carbon tracking method.
If you want to check specific method,
please do it in a sandbox because this
is a public preview.
Before I close the session, I just want
to remind you you have a lot of
interesting links. You can go there and
find interesting information.
One of the most important is LinkedIn.
We have updated information all the time
there or watch some of YouTube videos.
This is something where This is a place
where you find
BCLE and other videos from Microsoft as
well. So, thank you for watching this
session.